<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sreyfe.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://sreyfe.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-10-09T14:40:33+00:00</updated><id>https://sreyfe.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>My personal site.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Freud and Genesis 41</title><link href="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/freud-genesis-41/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freud and Genesis 41" /><published>2024-07-17T10:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-17T10:50:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/freud-genesis-41</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/freud-genesis-41/"><![CDATA[<p>A while back a friend gave me a very nice hardcover Suhrkamp of Freud’s <em>Mann Moses</em>, pictured below:</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/mann_moses.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>The volume (published in English as <em>Moses and Monotheism</em>) contains three essays published in the last
years of Freud’s life. He began to prepare the last of the three essays in Vienna, but only managed
to publish it after fleeing to England following the German invasion of Austria.</p>

<p>In case you aren’t familiar, this is Freud’s claim in a nutshell: Moses existed, but he was never 
a Jew. Instead, he was a high-ranking Egyptian who was loyal to a monotheistic cult which 
worshipped the sun god Aten, which was briefly the state religion of Egypt under 
Akhenaten. After Akhenaten’s death and the official reestablishment of polytheism, Moses 
decided to leave Egypt. He brought with him a Semitic tribe
(read: the forefathers of the Jews), upon whom he more-or-less forced his religion.
At some point in the desert, the proto-Jews rebelled and killed Moses. They then met up 
with related tribes and formed some sort of confederation. The Moses-religion was disavowed
but survived among the Levites, whom Freud claims were the clique of Egyptians that Moses brought 
along with him. At some point a couple of generations later, the proto-Jews take up the worship 
of a Midianite volcano-god named [ʀᴇᴅᴀᴄᴛᴇᴅ], under the direction of an unnamed
prophet. But the Moses-followers had grown in number and influence during the 
intervening generations, and so a compromise was made between them and the followers 
of the volcano-god. The new prophet was identified with Moses, and the attributes of
[ʀᴇᴅᴀᴄᴛᴇᴅ] and Aten were melted together. The murder of Moses then has all manner 
of psychoanalytic effects, sets the scene for Christianity, etc.</p>

<p>Freud himself repeatedly admits that the historical evidence for all this is 
rather sparse, but it seems he more-or-less believes it to be true. It’s a bit 
of a crackpot theory, but its very entertaining to read and good food for 
thought. Reading these essays feels a little like reading (forgive the comparison)
Däniken: you can’t really believe these fantastic claims about the
secret origins of the world we live in, but you’re glad to be along for the ride, and 
maybe there’s a little bit of truth in there somewhere… Or, perhaps to offend in the
other direction, Freud has written a sort of psychoanalytic Midrash which uses biblical
and historical scholarship, along with the Hebrew Bible itself, as building blocks.
Read as a parable, its shaky claim to historical truth becomes less important.</p>

<p>For textual support, Freud resorts to the work of Ed. Sellin, and <em>Mose und seine Bedeutung 
für die israelitisch-jüdische Religionsgeschichte</em> (1922) in particular. I haven’t read
the article, but apparently, there is evidence in <em>Hosea</em> and elsewhere that Moses 
was killed by the Israelites during one of their many (biblically documented) uprisings.
Here is Freud on Sellin:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Er fand beim Propheten Hosea (zweite Hälfte des achten Jahrhunderts) die unverkennbaren Anzeichen einer Tradition, die zum Inhalt hat, daß der Religionsstifter Moses in einem Aufstand seines widerspenstigen und halsstarrigen Volkes ein gewaltsames Ende fand. Gleichzeitig wurde die von ihm eingesetzte Religion abgeworfen. Diese Tradition ist aber nicht auf Hosea beschränkt, sie kehrt bei den meisten späteren Propheten wieder, ja, sie ist nach Sellin die Grundlage aller späteren messianischen Erwartungen geworden. Am Ausgang des babylonischen Exils entwickelte sich im jüdischen Volke die Hoffnung, der so schmählich Gemordete werde von den Toten wiederkommen und sein reuiges Volk, vielleicht dieses nicht allein, in das Reich einer dauernden Seligkeit führen. Die naheliegenden Beziehungen zum Schicksal eines späteren Religionsstifters liegen nicht auf unserem Weg. <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now, like I said, I don’t really believe this stuff, but nonetheless I think I’ve found 
a nice piece of evidence for Freud’s claims which he doesn’t mention. Last night I thought that 
it might be fun to read a random chapter of Genesis every day, and so today I put
the range 1-50 in a random number generator, got 41 as output, and sat down to 
read Genesis 41. This is the chapter where Joseph interprets Pharaoh’s dreams:
the scrawny cows eating the healthy cows, and the scrawny grain eating the healthy 
grain, both of which are so excellently illustrated by R. Crumb (below).</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/crumb_gen_41.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>As part of his reward for successfully interpreting Pharaoh’s dreams, in verse 45 
Joseph is married to Asenath, daughter of Poti-phera, <em>priest of On</em>. <sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>
On (aka Heliopolis) is mentioned repeatedly by Freud as the place of origin of 
the monotheistic worship of Aten which the Egyptian Moses practiced
and semi-successfully transmitted to his chosen Semitic tribe.</p>

<p>That the leader of the people Israel who preceded Moses was the son-in-law of a priest of 
Aten seems like a perfect piece of evidence for Freud. The lineage of Jewish leadership
dovetails with the lineage of Egyptian Aten priests! If Freud is to be believed, this is
to be read as a distorted confirmation that the origin of Jewish monotheism is Egyptian.
When coupled with the Traumdeutung which plays such a significant role in this chapter, it’s 
very strange that Freud left this out. I wonder if he knew of this chapter 
and, if so, what he thought of it…</p>

<p>Before I go, there’s a passage in the second essay that’s particularly cool, which may
or may not be related:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Es ist gewiß, daß recht verschiedene Elemente zum Aufbau des jüdischen Volkes zusammengetreten sind, aber den größten Unterschied unter diesen Stämmen muß es gemacht haben, ob sie den Aufenthalt in Ägypten, und was darauf folgte, miterlebt hatten oder nicht. Mit Rücksicht auf diesen Punkt kann man sagen, die Nation sei aus der Vereinigung von zwei Bestandteilen hervorgegangen, und dieser Tatsache entsprach es, daß sie auch nach einer kurzen Periode politischer Einheit in zwei Stücke, das Reich Israel und das Reich Juda, auseinanderbrach. Die Geschichte liebt solche Wiederherstellungen, in denen spätere Verschmelzungen rückgängig gemacht werden und frühere Trennungen wieder hervortreten. Das eindrucksvollste Beispiel dieser Art schuf bekanntlich die Reformation, als sie die Grenzlinie zwischen dem einst römisch gewesenen und dem unabhängig gebliebenen Germanien nach einem Intervall von mehr als einem Jahrtausend wieder zum Vorschein brachte. <sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Isn’t that nice? Pieces of the broken vessel, fitted together and painted over 
— but the crack is still there, just below the surface, waiting for just a 
little more pressure…</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Sigmund Freud, <em>Mann Moses</em>, Bibliothek Suhrkamp 131 (Berlin: Suhrkamp Verlag, 1970), 46-47. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Hebrew: וַיִּקְרָ֨א פַרְעֹ֣ה שֵׁם־יוֹסֵף֮ צָֽפְנַ֣ת פַּעְנֵ֒חַ֒ וַיִּתֶּן־ל֣וֹ אֶת־אָֽסְנַ֗ת בַּת־פּ֥וֹטִי פֶ֛רַע כֹּהֵ֥ן אֹ֖ן לְאִשָּׁ֑ה וַיֵּצֵ֥א יוֹסֵ֖ף עַל־אֶ֥רֶץ מִצְרָֽיִם׃ <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Freud, <em>Mann Moses</em>, 48 <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The priest of Aten is Joseph's Father-in-Law!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">James and Hazlitt</title><link href="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/james-hazlitt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="James and Hazlitt" /><published>2024-07-05T10:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-05T10:50:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/james-hazlitt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/james-hazlitt/"><![CDATA[<p>For about a week there, I was into cricket. Why exactly, I cannot say. Maybe it had to do with the T20 World Cup?
Though I didn’t know it was happening until I had already decided to watch cricket, it must have had something to do with it.
The coincidence is too striking. Maybe I saw an ad somewhere? Or there was something in the air? Maybe it was just
good luck. Having decided I would now watch cricket, I texted my friend Sidd to tell him of this change to my lifestyle
and he told me that the very next day he would be heading to New York to see the India vs. USA match. I watched, hoping
to see him in the crowd. The US fought nobly, but were defeated.</p>

<p>It seems there’s been a lot of interest in US cricket recently. This must be both cause and effect of the national teams recent (relative)
success. When I asked Sidd what was behind this, he told me “because there are a lot of Indians in Texas.” I can neither 
confirm nor deny. But I recently learned that cricket was once a much more popular sport in the US. The Wikipedia
article <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_cricket_in_the_United_States">History of cricket in the United States</a> asserts that there was a time when the game was significantly
more popular than baseball, and that “Abraham Lincoln, later to be President, had watched two American cities play each
other in an 1849 cricket match.”</p>

<p>But it is a weird and uncanny thing to see Americans play cricket. International cricket seems so bound-up
with the British Empire, especially the British Empire of the 19th century. What relation does Oman have with the West Indies, or Afghanistan
with Australia, besides British colonial power? And there is something vaguely maritime about the sport. The wicket, shaped
like the hull of a colossal ship, the bat like an oar… After Sloterdijk could we not say that cricket, with its emphasis on debts
accrued and repaid, on the attainment of exteriority, is the perfect game for the era of colonial globalization? And here, once 
more, are the Americans – returned to our native context?</p>

<p>But I know nothing of this. Who knows, is C. L. R. James, whose <em>Beyond a Boundary</em> I have wanted to read for a long time. This 
brush with cricket has finally given me the excuse. Borrowing a phrase from Kipling, James’s Leitsatz for the book is “What do 
they know of cricket who only cricket know?” In my case, it’s really “What do they know of cricket who know nothing of cricket?”
But anyway, the idea ist that cricket is a deeply ingrained practice in English society,
and in the society of the West Indies, among other places – that to understand cricket is to understand something fundamental
in these societies, and that, vice versa, in order to understand cricket, you need to understand a lot about societies. In other
words, the book explores cricket in all its contingencies with the world. James loved cricket, and though he is a professional
critic, he seems really to believe in the sport as a force for good, and this gives the book a sort of warm glow. If, like me,
you know nothing of cricket, a non-insignificant percentage of the books language will be incomprehensible to you (“silly mid-off”,
“on the back foot through the covers,” “slow bowler,” etc.), but there is something to enjoy here too. It’s a little like the 
<em>Voynich manuscript</em> or the <em>Codex Seraphianus,</em> or like a child looking at a printed page before they can read…</p>

<p>Of particular interest to me was James’s claim that, although cricket reached its height in Victorian England, it was not a 
Victorian game in either “origin or essence.” Instead, it came from an England that was</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>still unconquered by the Industrial Revolution. It travelled by saddle and carriage. Whenever it could
it ate and drank prodigiously. It was not finicky in morals. It enjoyed life. It prized the virtues of frankness, independence,
individuality, conviviality. There were rulers and ruled, the educated and the uneducated. If the two groupings could be
described as two nations they were neither of them conscious of the division as a state of things which ought not to be. <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve heard of this England… I think I read somewhere that in pre-Victorian Europe, England was once considered an
emotional, choleric nation, like Italy today. James asserts that Dickens is really a pre-Victorian, and this is what allowed
him to be such a good critic of Victorian England. But he believes that the great representative/representer of this era is Hazlitt.
He writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hazlitt was an intellectual to his fingertips, and a
militant, an extreme democrat who suffered martyrdom for his opinions.
Yet he is not a divided man, he has no acute consciousness either
of class or of divided culture. He discusses with equal verve the virtues
of a classical education and the ignorance of the learned. It is impossible
to distinguish any change in his style whether he writes on
William Cobbett, on his First Acquaintance with Poets, on John Cavanagh,
the Fives Player, or on the Fight between Bill Neate and the
Gas-man. It would be comparatively simple to maintain that his essay
on The Fight is his finest piece. It is what he called ‘a complete thing’,
giving such a picture of the England of his time as can nowhere else
be found in such a narrow compass. Wide as is his range, unlike the
late Robert Lynd or A. G. Gardiner (to mention two at random), he
does not fit his subject into a practised pattern. He takes his whole
self wherever he goes; he is ready to go everywhere; every new experience
renews and expands him. He writes as freely and as publicly of a
most degrading love-affair as of Elizabethan literature. The possibility
of such completeness of expression ended with him and has not yet
returned.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I had never heard of Hazlitt before James, like I had never heard of Browne before Borges. It’s always nice to get a recommendation
from a good writer, and it didn’t take long before I’d found <em>The Fight</em> and read it. It really is very good, and I have reproduced
it at the end of this post, for your reading pleasure, from the <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/72206">12th volume of Project Gutenberg’s Collected Works of William Hazlitt</a>.
What is good about it is what I think is good about good essays in general: contingency. In <em>The Fight</em>, Hazlitt is driven about 
by circumstance, and it is also circumstance or, as he might call it, FANCY, that informs his style. The essay makes no
claim to essential knowledge. Instead, it moves lightly from from idea to idea, always acknowledging the particular position of the
writer/narrator as he moves from London to the country by mail-coach and back again. This is what’s good about <em>Beyond a Boundary</em>
too. “Neither cricket reminiscences nor autobiography,” it revels in its contingency.</p>

<p><strong>THE FIGHT</strong></p>

<p><em>The New Monthly Magazine.</em> <em>February, 1822.</em></p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>        ‘——The fight, the fight’s the thing,
        Wherein I’ll catch the conscience of the king.’
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><em>Where there’s a will, there’s a way.</em>—I said so to myself, as I walked
down Chancery-lane, about half-past six o’clock on Monday the 10th of
December, to inquire at Jack Randall’s where the fight the next day was
to be; and I found ‘the proverb’ nothing ‘musty’ in the present
instance. I was determined to see this fight, come what would, and see
it I did, in great style. It was my <em>first fight</em>, yet it more than
answered my expectations. Ladies! it is to you I dedicate this
description; nor let it seem out of character for the fair to notice the
exploits of the brave. Courage and modesty are the old English virtues;
and may they never look cold and askance on one another! Think, ye
fairest of the fair, loveliest of the lovely kind, ye practisers of soft
enchantment, how many more ye kill with poisoned baits than ever fell in
the ring; and listen with subdued air and without shuddering, to a tale
tragic only in appearance, and sacred to the FANCY!</p>

<p>I was going down Chancery-lane, thinking to ask at Jack Randall’s where
the fight was to be, when looking through the glass-door of the <em>Hole in
the Wall</em>, I heard a gentleman asking the same question <em>at</em> Mrs.
Randall, as the author of Waverley would express it. Now Mrs. Randall
stood answering the gentleman’s question, with the authenticity of the
lady of the Champion of the Light Weights. Thinks I, I’ll wait till this
person comes out, and learn from him how it is. For to say a truth, I
was not fond of going into this house of call for heroes and
philosophers, ever since the owner of it (for Jack is no gentleman)
threatened once upon a time to kick me out of doors for wanting a
mutton-chop at his hospitable board, when the conqueror in thirteen
battles was more full of <em>blue ruin</em> than of good manners. I was the
more mortified at this repulse, inasmuch as I had heard Mr. James
Simpkins, hosier in the Strand, one day when the character of the <em>Hole
in the Wall</em> was brought in question, observe—‘The house is a very good
house, and the company quite genteel: I have been there myself!’
Remembering this unkind treatment of mine host, to which mine hostess
was also a party, and not wishing to put her in unquiet thoughts at a
time jubilant like the present, I waited at the door, when, who should
issue forth but my friend Jo. Toms, and turning suddenly up
Chancery-lane with that quick jerk and impatient stride which
distinguishes a lover of the FANCY, I said, ‘I’ll be hanged if that
fellow is not going to the fight, and is on his way to get me to go with
him.’ So it proved in effect, and we agreed to adjourn to my lodgings to
discuss measures with that cordiality which makes old friends like new,
and new friends like old, on great occasions. We are cold to others only
when we are dull in ourselves, and have neither thoughts nor feelings to
impart to them. Give a man a topic in his head, a throb of pleasure in
his heart, and he will be glad to share it with the first person he
meets. Toms and I, though we seldom meet, were an <em>alter idem</em> on this
memorable occasion, and had not an idea that we did not candidly impart;
and ‘so carelessly did we fleet the time,’ that I wish no better, when
there is another fight, than to have him for a companion on my journey
down, and to return with my friend Jack Pigott, talking of what was to
happen or of what did happen, with a noble subject always at hand, and
liberty to digress to others whenever they offered. Indeed, on my
repeating the lines from Spenser in an involuntary fit of enthusiasm,</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>           ‘What more felicity can fall to creature,
           Than to enjoy delight with liberty?’
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>my last-named ingenious friend stopped me by saying that this,
translated into the vulgate, meant ‘<em>Going to see a fight</em>.’</p>

<p>Jo. Toms and I could not settle about the method of going down. He said
there was a caravan, he understood, to start from Tom Belcher’s at two,
which would go there <em>right out</em> and back again the next day. Now I
never travel all night, and said I should get a cast to Newbury by one
of the mails. Jo. swore the thing was impossible, and I could only
answer that I had made up my mind to it. In short, he seemed to me to
waver, said he only came to see if I was going, had letters to write, a
cause coming on the day after, and faintly said at parting (for I was
bent on setting out that moment)—‘Well, we meet at Philippi!’ I made the
best of my way to Piccadilly. The mail-coach stand was bare. ‘They are
all gone,’ said I—‘this is always the way with me—in the instant I lose
the future—if I had not stayed to pour out that last cup of tea, I
should have been just in time’—and cursing my folly and ill-luck
together, without inquiring at the coach-office whether the mails were
gone or not, I walked on in despite, and to punish my own dilatoriness
and want of determination. At any rate, I would not turn back: I might
get to Hounslow, or perhaps farther, to be on my road the next morning.
I passed Hyde Park Corner (my Rubicon), and trusted to fortune. Suddenly
I heard the clattering of a Brentford stage, and the fight rushed full
upon my fancy. I argued (not unwisely) that even a Brentford coachman
was better company than my own thoughts (such as they were just then),
and at his invitation mounted the box with him. I immediately stated my
case to him—namely, my quarrel with myself for missing the Bath or
Bristol mail, and my determination to get on in consequence as well as I
could, without any disparagement or insulting comparison between longer
or shorter stages. It is a maxim with me that stage-coaches, and
consequently stage-coachmen, are respectable in proportion to the
distance they have to travel: so I said nothing on that subject to my
Brentford friend. Any incipient tendency to an abstract proposition, or
(as he might have construed it) to a personal reflection of this kind,
was however nipped in the bud; for I had no sooner declared indignantly
that I had missed the mails, than he flatly denied that they were gone
along, and lo! at the instant three of them drove by in rapid,
provoking, orderly succession, as if they would devour the ground before
them. Here again I seemed in the contradictory situation of the man in
Dryden who exclaims,</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>          ‘I follow Fate, which does too hard pursue!’
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>If I had stopped to inquire at the White Horse Cellar, which would not
have taken me a minute, I should now have been driving down the road in
all the dignified unconcern and <em>ideal</em> perfection of mechanical
conveyance. The Bath mail I had set my mind upon, and I had missed it,
as I missed every thing else, by my own absurdity, in putting the will
for the deed, and aiming at ends without employing means. ‘Sir,’ said he
of the Brentford, ‘the Bath mail will be up presently, my brother-in-law
drives it, and I will engage to stop him if there is a place empty.’ I
almost doubted my good genius; but, sure enough, up it drove like
lightning, and stopped directly at the call of the Brentford Jehu. I
would not have believed this possible, but the brother-in-law of a
mail-coach driver is himself no mean man. I was transferred without loss
of time from the top of one coach to that of the other, desired the
guard to pay my fare to the Brentford coachman for me as I had no
change, was accommodated with a great coat, put up my umbrella to keep
off a drizzling mist, and we began to cut through the air like an arrow.
The milestones disappeared one after another, the rain kept off; Tom
Turtle, the trainer, sat before me on the coach-box, with whom I
exchanged civilities as a gentleman going to the fight; the passion that
had transported me an hour before was subdued to pensive regret and
conjectural musing on the next day’s battle; I was promised a place
inside at Reading, and upon the whole, I thought myself a lucky fellow.
Such is the force of imagination! On the outside of any other coach on
the 10th of December, with a Scotch mist drizzling through the cloudy
moonlight air, I should have been cold, comfortless, impatient, and, no
doubt, wet through; but seated on the Royal mail, I felt warm and
comfortable, the air did me good, the ride did me good, I was pleased
with the progress we had made, and confident that all would go well
through the journey. When I got inside at Reading, I found Turtle and a
stout valetudinarian, whose costume bespoke him one of the FANCY, and
who had risen from a three months’ sick bed to get into the mail to see
the fight. They were intimate, and we fell into a lively discourse. My
friend the trainer was confined in his topics to fighting dogs and men,
to bears and badgers; beyond this he was ‘quite chap-fallen,’ had not a
word to throw at a dog, or indeed very wisely fell asleep, when any
other game was started. The whole art of training (I, however, learnt
from him,) consists in two things, exercise and abstinence, abstinence
and exercise, repeated alternately and without end. A yolk of an egg
with a spoonful of rum in it is the first thing in a morning, and then a
walk of six miles till breakfast. This meal consists of a plentiful
supply of tea and toast and beef-steaks. Then another six or seven miles
till dinner-time, and another supply of solid beef or mutton with a pint
of porter, and perhaps, at the utmost, a couple of glasses of sherry.
Martin trains on water, but this increases his infirmity on another very
dangerous side. The Gas-man takes now and then a chirping glass (under
the rose) to console him, during a six weeks’ probation, for the absence
of Mrs. Hickman—an agreeable woman, with (I understand) a pretty fortune
of two hundred pounds. How matter presses on me! What stubborn things
are facts! How inexhaustible is nature and art! ‘It is well,’ as I once
heard Mr. Richmond observe, ‘to see a variety.’ He was speaking of
cock-fighting as an edifying spectacle. I cannot deny but that one
learns more of what <em>is</em> (I do not say of what <em>ought to be</em>) in this
desultory mode of practical study, than from reading the same book twice
over, even though it should be a moral treatise. Where was I? I was
sitting at dinner with the candidate for the honours of the ring, ‘where
good digestion waits on appetite, and health on both.’ Then follows an
hour of social chat and native glee; and afterwards, to another
breathing over heathy hill or dale. Back to supper, and then to bed, and
up by six again—Our hero</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>                ‘Follows so the ever-running sun
                With profitable ardour‘—
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>to the day that brings him victory or defeat in the green fairy circle.
Is not this life more sweet than mine? I was going to say; but I will
not libel any life by comparing it to mine, which is (at the date of
these presents) bitter as coloquintida and the dregs of aconitum!</p>

<p>The invalid in the Bath mail soared a pitch above the trainer, and did
not sleep so sound, because he had ‘more figures and more fantasies.’ We
talked the hours away merrily. He had faith in surgery, for he had had
three ribs set right, that had been broken in a <em>turn-up</em> at Belcher’s,
but thought physicians old women, for they had no antidote in their
catalogue for brandy. An indigestion is an excellent common-place for
two people that never met before. By way of ingratiating myself, I told
him the story of my doctor, who, on my earnestly representing to him
that I thought his regimen had done me harm, assured me that the whole
pharmacopœia contained nothing comparable to the prescription he had
given me; and, as a proof of its undoubted efficacy, said, that, ‘he had
had one gentleman with my complaint under his hands for the last fifteen
years.’ This anecdote made my companion shake the rough sides of his
three great coats with boisterous laughter; and Turtle, starting out of
his sleep, swore he knew how the fight would go, for he had had a dream
about it. Sure enough the rascal told us how the three first rounds went
off, but ‘his dream,’ like others, ‘denoted a foregone conclusion.’ He
knew his men. The moon now rose in silver state, and I ventured, with
some hesitation, to point out this object of placid beauty, with the
blue serene beyond, to the man of science, to which his ear he
‘seriously inclined,’ the more as it gave promise <em>d’un beau jour</em> for
the morrow, and showed the ring undrenched by envious showers, arrayed
in sunny smiles. Just then, all going on well, I thought on my friend
Toms, whom I had left behind, and said innocently, ‘There was a
blockhead of a fellow I left in town, who said there was no possibility
of getting down by the mail, and talked of going by a caravan from
Belcher’s at two in the morning, after he had written some letters.’
‘Why,’ said he of the lapels, ‘I should not wonder if that was the very
person we saw running about like mad from one coach-door to another, and
asking if any one had seen a friend of his, a gentlemen going to the
fight, whom he had missed stupidly enough by staying to write a note.’
‘Pray, Sir,’ said my fellow-traveller, ‘had he a plaid-cloak on?’—‘Why,
no,’ said I, ‘not at the time I left him, but he very well might
afterwards, for he offered to lend me one.’ The plaid-cloak and the
letter decided the thing. Joe, sure enough, was in the Bristol mail,
which preceded us by about fifty yards. This was droll enough. We had
now but a few miles to our place of destination, and the first thing I
did on alighting at Newbury, both coaches stopping at the same time, was
to call out, ‘Pray, is there a gentleman in that mail of the name of
Toms?’ ‘No,’ said Joe, borrowing something of the vein of Gilpin, ‘for I
have just got out.’ ‘Well!’ says he, ‘this is lucky; but you don’t know
how vexed I was to miss you; for,’ added he, lowering his voice, ‘do you
know when I left you I went to Belcher’s to ask about the caravan, and
Mrs. Belcher said very obligingly, she couldn’t tell about that, but
there were two gentlemen who had taken places by the mail and were gone
on in a landau, and she could frank us. It’s a pity I didn’t meet with
you; we could then have got down for nothing. But <em>mum’s the word</em>.’
It’s the devil for any one to tell me a secret, for it’s sure to come
out in print. I do not care so much to gratify a friend, but the public
ear is too great a temptation to me.</p>

<p>Our present business was to get beds and a supper at an inn; but this
was no easy task. The public-houses were full, and where you saw a light
at a private house, and people poking their heads out of the casement to
see what was going on, they instantly put them in and shut the window,
the moment you seemed advancing with a suspicious overture for
accommodation. Our guard and coachman thundered away at the outer gate
of the Crown for some time without effect—such was the greater noise
within;—and when the doors were unbarred, and we got admittance, we
found a party assembled in the kitchen round a good hospitable fire,
some sleeping, others drinking, others talking on politics and on the
fight. A tall English yeoman (something like Matthews in the face, and
quite as great a wag)—</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>              ‘A lusty man to ben an abbot able,’—
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>was making such a prodigious noise about rent and taxes, and the price
of corn now and formerly, that he had prevented us from being heard at
the gate. The first thing I heard him say was to a shuffling fellow who
wanted to be off a bet for a shilling glass of brandy and
water—‘Confound it, man, don’t be <em>insipid</em>!’ Thinks I, that is a good
phrase. It was a good omen. He kept it up so all night, nor flinched
with the approach of morning. He was a fine fellow, with sense, wit, and
spirit, a hearty body and a joyous mind, free-spoken, frank,
convivial—one of that true English breed that went with Harry the Fifth
to the siege of Harfleur—‘standing like greyhounds in the slips,’ &amp;c. We
ordered tea and eggs (beds were soon found to be out of the question)
and this fellow’s conversation was <em>sauce piquante</em>. It did one’s heart
good to see him brandish his oaken towel and to hear him talk. He made
mince-meat of a drunken, stupid, red-faced, quarrelsome, <em>frowsy</em>
farmer, whose nose ‘he moralized into a thousand similes,’ making it out
a firebrand like Bardolph’s. ‘I’ll tell you what my friend,’ says he,
‘the landlady has only to keep you here to save fire and candle. If one
was to touch your nose, it would go off like a piece of charcoal.’ At
this the other only grinned like an idiot, the sole variety in his
purple face being his little peering grey eyes and yellow teeth; called
for another glass, swore he would not stand it; and after many attempts
to provoke his humourous antagonist to single combat, which the other
turned off (after working him up to a ludicrous pitch of choler) with
great adroitness, he fell quietly asleep with a glass of liquor in his
hand, which he could not lift to his head. His laughing persecutor made
a speech over him, and turning to the opposite side of the room, where
they were all sleeping in the midst of this ‘loud and furious fun,’
said, ‘There’s a scene, by G—d, for Hogarth to paint. I think he and
Shakspeare were our two best men at copying life.’ This confirmed me in
my good opinion of him. Hogarth, Shakspeare, and Nature, were just
enough for him (indeed for any man) to know. I said, ‘You read Cobbett,
don’t you? At least,’ says I, ‘you talk just as well as he writes.’ He
seemed to doubt this. But I said, ‘We have an hour to spare: if you’ll
get pen, ink, and paper, and keep on talking, I’ll write down what you
say; and if it doesn’t make a capital ‘Political Register,’ I’ll forfeit
my head. You have kept me alive to-night, however. I don’t know what I
should have done without you.’ He did not dislike this view of the
thing, nor my asking if he was not about the size of Jem Belcher; and
told me soon afterwards, in the confidence of friendship, that ‘the
circumstance which had given him nearly the greatest concern in his
life, was Cribb’s beating Jem after he had lost his eye by
racket-playing.’—The morning dawns; that dim but yet clear light
appears, which weighs like solid bars of metal on the sleepless eyelids;
the guests drop down from their chambers one by one—but it was too late
to think of going to bed now (the clock was on the stroke of seven), we
had nothing for it but to find a barber’s (the pole that glittered in
the morning sun lighted us to his shop), and then a nine miles’ march to
Hungerford. The day was fine, the sky was blue, the mists were retiring
from the marshy ground, the path was tolerably dry, the sitting-up all
night had not done us much harm—at least the cause was good; we talked
of this and that with amicable difference, roving and sipping of many
subjects, but still invariably we returned to the fight. At length, a
mile to the left of Hungerford, on a gentle eminence, we saw the ring
surrounded by covered carts, gigs, and carriages, of which hundreds had
passed us on the road; Toms gave a youthful shout, and we hastened down
a narrow lane to the scene of action.</p>

<p>Reader, have you ever seen a fight? If not, you have a pleasure to come,
at least if it is a fight like that between the Gas-man and Bill Neate.
The crowd was very great when we arrived on the spot; open carriages
were coming up, with streamers flying and music playing, and the country
people were pouring in over hedge and ditch in all directions, to see
their hero beat or be beaten. The odds were still on Gas, but only about
five to four. Gully had been down to try Neate, and had backed him
considerably, which was a damper to the sanguine confidence of the
adverse party. About two hundred thousand pounds were pending. The Gas
says, he has lost 3000<em>l.</em> which were promised him by different
gentlemen if he had won. He had presumed too much on himself, which had
made others presume on him. This spirited and formidable young fellow
seems to have taken for his motto the old maxim, that ‘there are three
things necessary to success in life—<em>Impudence! Impudence! Impudence!</em>’
It is so in matters of opinion, but not in the <em>Fancy</em>, which is the
most practical of all things, though even here confidence is half the
battle, but only half. Our friend had vapoured and swaggered too much,
as if he wanted to grin and bully his adversary out of the fight. ‘Alas!
the Bristol man was not so tamed!’—‘This is <em>the grave-digger</em>’ (would
Tom Hickman exclaim in the moments of intoxication from gin and success,
shewing his tremendous right hand), ‘this will send many of them to
their long homes; I haven’t done with them yet! ‘Why should he—though he
had licked four of the best men within the hour, yet why should he
threaten to inflict dishonourable chastisement on my old master
Richmond, a veteran going off the stage, and who has borne his sable
honours meekly? Magnanimity, my dear Tom, and bravery, should be
inseparable. Or why should he go up to his antagonist, the first time he
ever saw him at the Fives Court, and measuring him from head to foot
with a glance of contempt, as Achilles surveyed Hector, say to him,
‘What, are you Bill Neate? I’ll knock more blood out of that great
carcase of thine, this day fortnight, than you ever knock’d out of a
bullock’s!’ It was not manly, ’twas not fighter-like. If he was sure of
the victory (as he was not), the less said about it the better. Modesty
should accompany the <em>Fancy</em> as its shadow. The best men were always the
best behaved. Jem Belcher, the Game Chicken (before whom the Gas-man
could not have lived) were civil, silent men. So is Cribb, so is Tom
Belcher, the most elegant of sparrers, and not a man for every one to
take by the nose. I enlarged on this topic in the mail (while Turtle was
asleep), and said very wisely (as I thought) that impertinence was a
part of no profession. A boxer was bound to beat his man, but not to
thrust his fist, either actually or by implication, in every one’s face.
Even a highwayman, in the way of trade, may blow out your brains, but if
he uses foul language at the same time, I should say he was no
gentleman. A boxer, I would infer, need not be a blackguard or a
coxcomb, more than another. Perhaps I press this point too much on a
fallen man—Mr. Thomas Hickman has by this time learnt that first of all
lessons, ‘That man was made to mourn.’ He has lost nothing by the late
fight but his presumption; and that every man may do as well without! By
an over-display of this quality, however, the public had been prejudiced
against him, and the <em>knowing-ones</em> were taken in. Few but those who had
bet on him wished Gas to win. With my own prepossessions on the subject,
the result of the 11th of December appeared to me as fine a piece of
poetical justice as I had ever witnessed. The difference of weight
between the two combatants (14 stone to 12) was nothing to the sporting
men. Great, heavy, clumsy, long-armed Bill Neate kicked the beam in the
scale of the Gas-man’s vanity. The amateurs were frightened at his big
words, and thought that they would make up for the difference of six
feet and five feet nine. Truly, the FANCY are not men of imagination.
They judge of what has been, and cannot conceive of anything that is to
be. The Gas-man had won hitherto; therefore he must beat a man half as
big again as himself—and that to a certainty. Besides, there are as many
feuds, factions, prejudices, pedantic notions in the FANCY as in the
state or in the schools. Mr. Gully is almost the only cool, sensible man
among them, who exercises an unbiassed discretion, and is not a slave to
his passions in these matters. But enough of reflections, and to our
tale. The day, as I have said, was fine for a December morning. The
grass was wet, and the ground miry, and ploughed up with multitudinous
feet, except that, within the ring itself, there was a spot of
virgin-green closed in and unprofaned by vulgar tread, that shone with
dazzling brightness in the mid-day sun. For it was now noon, and we had
an hour to wait. This is the trying time. It is then the heart sickens,
as you think what the two champions are about, and how short a time will
determine their fate. After the first blow is struck, there is no
opportunity for nervous apprehensions; you are swallowed up in the
immediate interest of the scene—but</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>            ‘Between the acting of a dreadful thing
            And the first motion, all the interim is
            Like a phantasma, or a hideous dream.’
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I found it so as I felt the sun’s rays clinging to my back, and saw the
white wintry clouds sink below the verge of the horizon. ‘So, I thought,
my fairest hopes have faded from my sight!—so will the Gas-man’s glory,
or that of his adversary, vanish in an hour.’ The <em>swells</em> were parading
in their white box-coats, the outer ring was cleared with some bruises
on the heads and shins of the rustic assembly (for the <em>cockneys</em> had
been distanced by the sixty-six miles); the time drew near, I had got a
good stand; a bustle, a buzz, ran through the crowd, and from the
opposite side entered Neate, between his second and bottle-holder. He
rolled along, swathed in his loose great coat, his knock-knees bending
under his huge bulk; and, with a modest cheerful air, threw his hat into
the ring. He then just looked round, and began quietly to undress; when
from the other side there was a similar rush and an opening made, and
the Gas-man came forward with a conscious air of anticipated triumph,
too much like the cock-of-the walk. He strutted about more than became a
hero, sucked oranges with a supercilious air, and threw away the skin
with a toss of his head, and went up and looked at Neate, which was an
act of supererogation. The only sensible thing he did was, as he strode
away from the modern Ajax, to fling out his arms, as if he wanted to try
whether they would do their work that day. By this time they had
stripped, and presented a strong contrast in appearance. If Neate was
like Ajax, ‘with Atlantean shoulders, fit to bear’ the pugilistic
reputation of all Bristol, Hickman might be compared to Diomed, light,
vigorous, elastic, and his back glistened in the sun, as he moved about,
like a panther’s hide. There was now a dead pause—attention was
awe-struck. Who at that moment, big with a great event, did not draw his
breath short—did not feel his heart throb? All was ready. They tossed up
for the sun, and the Gas-man won. They were led up to the
<em>scratch</em>—shook hands, and went at it.</p>

<p>In the first round every one thought it was all over. After making play
a short time, the Gas-man flew at his adversary like a tiger, struck
five blows in as many seconds, three first, and then following him as he
staggered back, two more, right and left, and down he fell, a mighty
ruin. There was a shout, and I said, ‘There is no standing this.’ Neate
seemed like a lifeless lump of flesh and bone, round which the Gas-man’s
blows played with the rapidity of electricity or lightning, and you
imagined he would only be lifted up to be knocked down again. It was as
if Hickman held a sword or a fire in that right hand of his, and
directed it against an unarmed body. They met again, and Neate seemed,
not cowed, but particularly cautious. I saw his teeth clenched together
and his brows knit close against the sun. He held out both his arms at
full length straight before him, like two sledge-hammers, and raised his
left an inch or two higher. The Gas-man could not get over this
guard—they struck mutually and fell, but without advantage on either
side. It was the same in the next round; but the balance of power was
thus restored—the fate of the battle was suspended. No one could tell
how it would end. This was the only moment in which opinion was divided;
for, in the next, the Gas-man aiming a mortal blow at his adversary’s
neck, with his right hand, and failing from the length he had to reach,
the other returned it with his left at full swing, planted a tremendous
blow on his cheek-bone and eyebrow, and made a red ruin of that side of
his face. The Gas-man went down, and there was another shout—a roar of
triumph as the waves of fortune rolled tumultuously from side to side.
This was a settler. Hickman got up, and ‘grinned horrible a ghastly
smile,’ yet he was evidently dashed in his opinion of himself; it was
the first time he had ever been so punished; all one side of his face
was perfect scarlet, and his right eye was closed in dingy blackness, as
he advanced to the fight, less confident, but still determined. After
one or two rounds, not receiving another such remembrancer, he rallied
and went at it with his former impetuosity. But in vain. His strength
had been weakened,—his blows could not tell at such a distance,—he was
obliged to fling himself at his adversary, and could not strike from his
feet; and almost as regularly as he flew at him with his right hand,
Neate warded the blow, or drew back out of its reach, and felled him
with the return of his left. There was little cautious sparring—no
half-hits—no tapping and trifling, none of the <em>petit-maitreship</em> of the
art—they were almost all knock-down blows:—the fight was a good stand-up
fight. The wonder was the half-minute time. If there had been a minute
or more allowed between each round, it would have been intelligible how
they should by degrees recover strength and resolution; but to see two
men smashed to the ground, smeared with gore, stunned, senseless, the
breath beaten out of their bodies; and then, before you recover from the
shock, to see them rise up with new strength and courage, stand steady
to inflict or receive mortal offence, and rush upon each other ‘like two
clouds over the Caspian’—this is the most astonishing thing of all:—this
is the high and heroic state of man! From this time forward the event
became more certain every round; and about the twelfth it seemed as if
it must have been over. Hickman generally stood with his back to me; but
in the scuffle, he had changed positions, and Neate just then made a
tremendous lunge at him, and hit him full in the face. It was doubtful
whether he would fall backwards or forwards; he hung suspended for a
second or two, and then fell back, throwing his hands in the air, and
with his face lifted up to the sky. I never saw any thing more terrific
than his aspect just before he fell. All traces of life, of natural
expression, were gone from him. His face was like a human skull, a
death’s head, spouting blood. The eyes were filled with blood, the nose
streamed with blood, the mouth gaped blood. He was not like an actual
man, but like a preternatural, spectral appearance, or like one of the
figures in Dante’s <em>Inferno</em>. Yet he fought on after this for several
rounds, still striking the first desperate blow, and Neate standing on
the defensive, and using the same cautious guard to the last, as if he
had still all his work to do; and it was not till the Gas-man was so
stunned in the seventeenth or eighteenth round, that his senses forsook
him, and he could not come to time, that the battle was declared
over.[3] Ye who despise the Fancy, do something to shew as much <em>pluck</em>,
or as much self-possession as this, before you assume a superiority
which you have never given a single proof of by any one action in the
whole course of your lives!—When the Gas-man came to himself, the first
words he uttered were, ‘Where am I? What is the matter?’ ‘Nothing is the
matter, Tom,—you have lost the battle, but you are the bravest man
alive.’ And Jackson whispered to him, ‘I am collecting a purse for you,
Tom.’—Vain sounds, and unheard at that moment! Neate instantly went up
and shook him cordially by the hand, and seeing some old acquaintance,
began to flourish with his fists, calling out, ‘Ah you always said I
couldn’t fight—What do you think now?’ But all in good humour, and
without any appearance of arrogance; only it was evident Bill Neate was
pleased that he had won the fight. When it was over, I asked Cribb if he
did not think it was a good one? He said, ‘<em>Pretty well!</em>’ The
carrier-pigeons now mounted into the air, and one of them flew with the
news of her husband’s victory to the bosom of Mrs. Neate. Alas, for Mrs.
Hickman!</p>

<p><em>Mais au revoir</em>, as Sir Fopling Flutter says. I went down with Toms; I
returned with Jack Pigott, whom I met on the ground. Toms is a rattle
brain; Pigott is a sentimentalist. Now, under favour, I am a
sentimentalist too—therefore I say nothing, but that the interest of the
excursion did not flag as I came back. Pigott and I marched along the
causeway leading from Hungerford to Newbury, now observing the effect of
a brilliant sun on the tawny meads or moss-coloured cottages, now
exulting in the fight, now digressing to some topic of general and
elegant literature. My friend was dressed in character for the occasion,
or like one of the FANCY; that is, with a double portion of great coats,
clogs, and overhauls: and just as we had agreed with a couple of country
lads to carry his superfluous wearing apparel to the next town, we were
overtaken by a return post-chaise, into which I got, Pigott preferring a
seat on the bar. There were two strangers already in the chaise, and on
their observing they supposed I had been to the fight, I said I had, and
concluded they had done the same. They appeared, however, a little shy
and sore on the subject; and it was not till after several hints
dropped, and questions put, that it turned out that they had missed it.
One of these friends had undertaken to drive the other there in his gig:
they had set out, to make sure work, the day before at three in the
afternoon. The owner of the one-horse vehicle scorned to ask his way,
and drove right on to Bagshot, instead of turning off at Hounslow: there
they stopped all night, and set off the next day across the country to
Reading, from whence they took coach, and got down within a mile or two
of Hungerford, just half an hour after the fight was over. This might be
safely set down as one of the miseries of human life. We parted with
these two gentlemen who had been to see the fight, but had returned as
they went, at Wolhampton, where we were promised beds (an irresistible
temptation, for Pigott had passed the preceding night at Hungerford as
we had done at Newbury), and we turned into an old bow-windowed parlour
with a carpet and a snug fire; and after devouring a quantity of tea,
toast, and eggs, sat down to consider, during an hour of philosophic
leisure, what we should have for supper. In the midst of an Epicurean
deliberation between a roasted fowl and mutton chops with mashed
potatoes, we were interrupted by an inroad of Goths and Vandals—<em>O
procul este profani</em>—not real flash-men, but interlopers, noisy
pretenders, butchers from Tothill-fields, brokers from Whitechapel, who
called immediately for pipes and tobacco, hoping it would not be
disagreeable to the gentlemen, and began to insist that it was <em>a
cross</em>. Pigott withdrew from the smoke and noise into another room, and
left me to dispute the point with them for a couple of hours <em>sans
intermission</em> by the dial. The next morning we rose refreshed; and on
observing that Jack had a pocket volume in his hand, in which he read in
the intervals of our discourse, I inquired what it was, and learned to
my particular satisfaction that it was a volume of the New Eloise.
Ladies, after this, will you contend that a love for the FANCY is
incompatible with the cultivation of sentiment?—We jogged on as before,
my friend setting me up in a genteel drab great coat and green silk
handkerchief (which I must say became me exceedingly), and after
stretching our legs for a few miles, and seeing Jack Randall, Ned
Turner, and Scroggins, pass on the top of one of the Bath coaches, we
engaged with the driver of the second to take us to London for the usual
fee. I got inside, and found three other passengers. One of them was an
old gentleman with an aquiline nose, powdered hair, and a pigtail, and
who looked as if he had played many a rubber at the Bath rooms. I said
to myself, he is very like Mr. Windham; I wish he would enter into
conversation, that I might hear what fine observations would come from
those finely-turned features. However, nothing passed, till, stopping to
dine at Reading, some inquiry was made by the company about the fight,
and I gave (as the reader may believe) an eloquent and animated
description of it. When we got into the coach again, the old gentleman,
after a graceful exordium, said, he had, when a boy, been to a fight
between the famous Broughton and George Stevenson, who was called the
<em>Fighting Coachman</em>, in the year 1770, with the late Mr. Windham. This
beginning flattered the spirit of prophecy within me and rivetted my
attention. He went on—‘George Stevenson was coachman to a friend of my
father’s. He was an old man when I saw him some years afterwards. He
took hold of his own arm and said, “there was muscle here once, but now
it is no more than this young gentleman’s.” He added, “well, no matter;
I have been here long, I am willing to go hence, and I hope I have done
no more harm than another man.” Once,’ said my unknown companion, ‘I
asked him if he had ever beat Broughton? He said Yes; that he had fought
with him three times, and the last time he fairly beat him, though the
world did not allow it. “I’ll tell you how it was, master. When the
seconds lifted us up in the last round, we were so exhausted that
neither of us could stand, and we fell upon one another, and as Master
Broughton fell uppermost, the mob gave it in his favour, and he was said
to have won the battle. But,” says he, “the fact was, that as his second
(John Cuthbert) lifted him up, he said to him, ‘I’ll fight no more, I’ve
had enough;’ which,” says Stevenson, “you know gave me the victory. And
to prove to you that this was the case, when John Cuthbert was on his
death-bed, and they asked him if there was any thing on his mind which
he wished to confess, he answered, ‘Yes, that there was one thing he
wished to set right, for that certainly Master Stevenson won that last
fight with Master Broughton; for he whispered him as he lifted him up in
the last round of all, that he had had enough.’”’ ‘This,’ said the Bath
gentleman, ‘was a bit of human nature;’ and I have written this account
of the fight on purpose that it might not be lost to the world. He also
stated as a proof of the candour of mind in this class of men, that
Stevenson acknowledged that Broughton could have beat him in his best
day; but that he (Broughton) was getting old in their last rencounter.
When we stopped in Piccadilly, I wanted to ask the gentleman some
questions about the late Mr. Windham, but had not courage. I got out,
resigned my coat and green silk handkerchief to Pigott (loth to part
with these ornaments of life), and walked home in high spirits.</p>

<p>P.S. Toms called upon me the next day, to ask me if I did not think the
fight was a complete thing? I said I thought it was. I hope he will
relish my account of it.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>C. L. R. James, <em>Beyond a Boundary: 50th Anniversary Edition</em>, The C. L. R. James Archives (Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 2013), 159. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Ibid., 160 <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cricket, C. L. R. James, The Fight by Hazlitt]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter Frequency II – Visualizations</title><link href="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/letter-frequency_2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter Frequency II – Visualizations" /><published>2024-05-02T10:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T10:50:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/letter-frequency_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/letter-frequency_2/"><![CDATA[<p>In order to better procrastinate on my master’s thesis (an analysis of <a href="https://iberz.org/">my database of translations into Yiddish</a>), I’ve been getting into Rust and cellular automata. I have been thinking vaguely about how automata could be used to model literary production. Maybe a big bimodal graph of translators and publishers, with rules governing when publishers are born/die/survive? More to be seen…</p>

<p>But I think I just like how cellular automata look. I used to throw text data into .bmp’s and see what would come out, and these representations of one dimensional cellular automata, with their strange periodicities, have a similar feel.</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/cell_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>Remembering, this I thought to myself: why not use these methods to take a look at the Hebrew Bible? My first idea was to convert each Hebrew letter to a numerical, then binary representation. א, as the first letter, would be 0 or 00000 as expressed in five bit binary. ב would then be 00001, ג would be 00010, all the way up through ת (10101). Final letters are encoded as their normal forms. I would then write all these binary representations to an image in the wonderful <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netpbm">.pbm format</a>.</p>

<p>In case you’re not familiar, .pbm, .pgm, and .ppm have ASCII formats, which makes them very human readable and fun to manipulate. A file that looks like this:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>P1
# This is an example bitmap of the letter "J"
6 10
0 0 0 0 1 0
0 0 0 0 1 0
0 0 0 0 1 0
0 0 0 0 1 0
0 0 0 0 1 0
0 0 0 0 1 0
1 0 0 0 1 0
0 1 1 1 0 0
0 0 0 0 0 0
0 0 0 0 0 0
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Will end up looking like this:
<br /><br />
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ad/Example_of_ASCII-art_turned_into_a_bitmap_scale20.pbm.png" /></p>

<p>Pretty cool, right? A five-bit, square representation of Genesis 1 encoded this way looks like this:</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/genesis_1_bw.png" class=" z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>From left to right it reads:</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>00001</td>
      <td>10011</td>
      <td>00000</td>
      <td>10100</td>
      <td>01001</td>
      <td>10101</td>
      <td>…</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>ב</td>
      <td>ר</td>
      <td>א</td>
      <td>ש</td>
      <td>י</td>
      <td>ת</td>
      <td>…</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Cool as this looks (to me anyway…), our eyes are really quite ill-equipped to read any of it. If you want you can sit there and decode byte by byte, but its very difficult to find patterns. But if we introduce color, patterns start to emerge.</p>

<p>So I decided to do the same basic thing but represent each of the 22 letters of the Hebrew alphabet with a different color. As luck would have it, <a href="https://gist.github.com/Myndex/997244b95d84788df96f4aab8b9edeb1">in 1965 one Kenneth Kelly defined a 22-color palette designed for maximum contrast</a>. I modified my code to use the colorful .ppm format, and began producing representations like this (read right to left):</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/genesis_1.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>Genesis 1</p>

<p>The letter/color key is as follows:</p>

<h2 style="direction: rtl; text-align: right">
<span style="background-color:#FDFDFD; border: solid; border-width: 1px;">א</span>
<span style="background-color:#1d1d1d; color:white;  border: solid">ב</span>
<span style="background-color:#ebce2b; color:white">ג</span>
<span style="background-color:#702c8c; color:white">ד</span>
<span style="background-color:#db6917; color:white">ה</span>
<span style="background-color:#96cde6; color:white">ו</span>
<span style="background-color:#ba1c30; color:white">ז</span>
<span style="background-color:#c0bd7f; color:white">ח</span>
<span style="background-color:#7f7e80; color:white">ת</span>
<span style="background-color:#5fa641; color:white">י</span>
<span style="background-color:#d485b2; color:white">כך</span>
<span style="background-color:#4277b6; color:white">ל</span>
<span style="background-color:#df8461; color:white">מם</span>
<span style="background-color:#463397; color:white">נן</span>
<span style="background-color:#e1a11a; color:white">ס</span>
<span style="background-color:#91218c; color:white">ע</span>
<span style="background-color:#e8e948; color:white">פף</span>
<span style="background-color:#7e1510; color:white">צץ</span>
<span style="background-color:#92ae31; color:white">ק</span>
<span style="background-color:#6f340d; color:white">ר</span>
<span style="background-color:#d32b1e; color:white">ש</span>
<span style="background-color:#2b3514; color:white">ת</span>
</h2>
<p><br />
It’s still not the easiest thing to read, but some interesting patterns emerge. As mentioned in the <a href="/blog/2024/letter-frequency/">previous blog post</a>, there are a lot of yuds in Genesis 1, and accordingly the above representation is marbled thoroughly with a <span style="background-color:#5fa641;">nice green</span>. Due to its consecutive use, vav, which is represented with <span style="background-color:#96cde6;">light blue</span>, tends to form nice, evenly spaced, diagonal striations. It also tends to be the first color in most chapters, as in Genesis 11 and 19:</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/genesis_11.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>Genesis 11</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/genesis_19.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>Genesis 19</p>

<p>ה, in <span style="background-color:#db6917; color:white">orange</span>, is also sprinkled evenly throughout, as are <span style="background-color:#FDFDFD; border: solid; border-width: 1px;">aleph</span> and <span style="background-color:#2b3514; color:white">tav</span>. When you look at these diagrams for long enough, you can start to pick out all the את’s, which are represented by a white square followed by a dark gray-green square.</p>

<p>I also decided to make representations of individual verses, in order to take a look at some of the conclusions I made last time. And, as expected, Gen 10:28 is white with <span style="border: solid; border-width: 1px;">alephs</span>:</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/10-28.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>Gen 1:23 is green with <span style="background-color:#5fa641; color:white">yuds</span>:</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/1-23.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>Gen 49:19, the prophecy of Gad, has sort of a jester/Lakers look, due to the high occurence of <span style="background-color:#ebce2b; color:white">gimel</span> and
<span style="background-color:#702c8c; color:white">daled</span>.</p>

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/49-19.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<p>This approach enables an interesting mix of very close and very distant reading. It highlights the smallest unit of Hebrew (the letter), and makes it visible over large swathes of text.</p>

<p>Can it help us learn anything? I’m not sure… But it sure does look cool. If you’re interested, the code and all the images are available on my <a href="https://github.com/sreyfe/hebrew_bible_frequencies/tree/main/visualizations">GitHub</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My second look at letter frequency, this time in Rust and with cool visualizations]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter frequency by verse in Genesis</title><link href="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/letter-frequency/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter frequency by verse in Genesis" /><published>2024-04-15T10:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T10:50:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/letter-frequency</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sreyfe.github.io/blog/2024/letter-frequency/"><![CDATA[<p>The other morning, still half-asleep, addled by a recent interest in the Masora and participation in the very interesting <a href="https://www.mmz-potsdam.de/aktuelles/veranstaltungen/2024/the-value-of-the-digital-dhjewish-conference-and-hackathon">DHJewish conference</a> in Potsdam, I thought to myself: “you know, there’s been a lot said about the Hebrew Bible beginning with ב and not with א, but aren’t there a lot of א’s in Genesis 1:1 anyway? There’s one in every word except השמים… Maybe Genesis 1:1 is actually the verse in Genesis with the highest frequency of א…”</p>

<p>In order to check this, I took the unvocalized text of Genesis from Sefaria. For each verse, I divided the occurence of each letter by the total number of letters in the verse (treating final and non-final as the same letter). This gave me a measure of frequency, which I then ranked.</p>

<p>So, is Genesis 1:1 the verse with the highest frequency of א? Nope, it’s in 13th place. Nonetheless, this little investigation turned up some interesting patterns. With the caveats that modern verse divisions are a pretty late addition, and short verses are over-represented, here are some of the more interesting ones:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>ג and ד are most frequent in the same verse: 49:19, wherein Jacob gives a prophecy for his son Gad (גד), punning repeatedly on his name.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>four out of five of the top-five verses for י are in Genesis 1. We can attribute this at least partly to the formulaic ויהי ערב ויהי בקר and the yuddiness of ordinal numbers (חמישי, רביעי). But 1:6, which is in 5th place, has neither ויהי ערב ויהי בקר nor ordinal numbers. Neither does 1:8, which is in 6th place… Perhaps the frequency of י here can be attributed to all the jussives, plus the repeated presence of “elohim?” Considering the importance of י, this one’s a little spooky… It would be interesting to see if Genesis 1 was the chapter with the highest י frequency. A task for another day…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>the top-four verses in terms of פ-frequency are all from Genesis 36, owing to the repetition of אלוף.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The verse with the highest frequency of ט has a frequency of only 0.060606 (36:22), the lowest of any letter. ז follows with 0.062500 (25:29). The letter with the highest frequency in a single verse is י, with 1:23 and 1:19 both having a frequency of 0.318181.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Below is a table indicating the verse with the highest frequency of a single letter. For a JSON with all this data, see the counts.json file <a href="https://github.com/sreyfe/hebrew_bible_frequencies">in this repo</a>.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: right">Letter</th>
      <th>Verse (Genesis)</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">Text</th>
      <th>Frequency</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">א</td>
      <td>10:28</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ואת עובל ואת אבימאל ואת שבא</td>
      <td>0.272727</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ב</td>
      <td>43:1</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">והרעב כבד בארץ</td>
      <td>0.250000</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ג</td>
      <td>49:19</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">גד גדוד יגודנו והוא יגד עקב</td>
      <td>0.181818</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ד</td>
      <td>49:19</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">גד גדוד יגודנו והוא יגד עקב</td>
      <td>0.227273</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ה</td>
      <td>7:8</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">מן הבהמה הטהורה ומן הבהמה אשר איננה טהרה ומן העוף וכל אשר רמש על האדמה</td>
      <td>0.267857</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ו (tie)</td>
      <td>8:18</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויצא נח ובניו ואשתו ונשי בניו אתו</td>
      <td>0.296296</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ו (tie)</td>
      <td>46:13</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ובני יששכר תולע ופוה ויוב ושמרון</td>
      <td>0.296296</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ז</td>
      <td>25:29</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויזד יעקב נזיד ויבא עשו מן השדה והוא עיף</td>
      <td>0.062500</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ח</td>
      <td>5:21</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויחי חנוך חמש וששים שנה ויולד את מתושלח</td>
      <td>0.125000</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ט</td>
      <td>36:22</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויהיו בני לוטן חרי והימם ואחות לוטן תמנע</td>
      <td>0.060606</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">י (tie)</td>
      <td>1:23</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויהי ערב ויהי בקר יום חמישי</td>
      <td>0.318181</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">י (tie)</td>
      <td>1:19</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויהי ערב ויהי בקר יום רביעי</td>
      <td>0.318181</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">כ</td>
      <td>34:15</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">אך בזאת נאות לכם אם תהיו כמנו להמל לכם כל זכר</td>
      <td>0.171429</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ל</td>
      <td>6:21</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ואתה קח לך מכל מאכל אשר יאכל ואספת אליך והיה</td>
      <td>0.195652</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">מ</td>
      <td>25:14</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ומשמע ודומה ומשא</td>
      <td>0.285714</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">נ</td>
      <td>9:14</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">והיה בענני ענן על הארץ ונראתה הקשת בענן</td>
      <td>0.218750</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ס</td>
      <td>12:9</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויסע אברם הלוך ונסוע הנגבה</td>
      <td>0.090909</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ע</td>
      <td>44:33</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ועתה ישב נא עבדך תחת הנער עבד לאדני והנער יעל</td>
      <td>0.166667</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">פ</td>
      <td>36:41</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">אלוף אהליבמה אלוף אלה אלוף פינן</td>
      <td>0.153846</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">צ</td>
      <td>19:23</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">השמש יצא על הארץ ולוט בא צערה</td>
      <td>0.130435</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ק</td>
      <td>15:19</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">את הקיני ואת הקנזי ואת הקדמני</td>
      <td>0.125000</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ר (tie)</td>
      <td>9:7</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ואתם פרו ורבו שרצו בארץ ורבו בה</td>
      <td>0.200000</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ר (tie)</td>
      <td>14:6</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ואת החרי בהררם שעיר עד איל פארן אשר על המדבר</td>
      <td>0.200000</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ש</td>
      <td>5:23</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">ויהי כל ימי חנוך חמש וששים שנה ושלש מאות שנה</td>
      <td>0.200000</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: right">ת</td>
      <td>34:9</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">והתחתנו אתנו בנתיכם תתנו לנו ואת בנתינו תקחו לכם</td>
      <td>0.225000</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a brief look at letter frequency in Genesis]]></summary></entry></feed>